[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Twenty-one]
[第二十一集]
President Xu Shichang has asked me to tell you all
徐世昌总统让我转告大家
that the feelings and wishes of the government of the Republic of China and the Qingdao citizens
民国政府和青岛民众的心情
[Wang Daxie, styled Botang, Chairman of the Foreign Affairs Committee of the Republic of China]
[汪大燮 字伯棠 中华民国外交委员会委员长]
are the same.
和愿望是一致的
The government delegation of the Republic of China
参加巴黎和会的
attending the Paris Peace Conference
中华民国政府代表团
has successfully arrived in Paris.
已经顺利地到达了巴黎
They will discuss and solve
他们将和各战胜国一起
the relations and interests between China and Germany after the war
商讨并解决
with the victorious countries,
战后中国和德国的关系和利益
to safeguard China's sovereignty and the interests of the people.
维护中国的主权和民众的利益
The ambassadors to the United States, Britain, France and Italy,
美 英 法 意四国的驻华公使
asked me to send greetings to you all
闻讯以后
when they heard about this.
都请我向大家致意
They will uphold the principle of fairness and justice,
他们将秉承公正正义的原则
safeguard China's sovereignty,
维护中国的主权
guarantee the territorial integrity of big and small countries
保证大小国家领土完整
and their political independence.
和政治独立
So we have reason to believe
因此我们有理由相信
that in the near future,
在不远的将来
the Shandong Peninsula will be completely returned to China.
山东半岛将会完整地交还给中国
Hurrah!
好
Because
因为
we are, after all,
我们毕竟是
victorious in this world war.
这场世界大战的胜利者
We have a chance to claim the fruits of victory.
我们有理由得到胜利的果实
Long live China! Long live China!
中国万岁 中国万岁
Long live China! Long live China! Long live China!
中国万岁 中国万岁 中国万岁
On the verge of success,
眼看就要成功了
the fact that
偏偏闹出这么档子事来
Cai Yuanpei and Chen Duxiu had made such a mess,
这个蔡元培和陈独秀他们
is really exploitative and pervasive.
真是能见缝插针 无孔不入
Didn't the National Assembly already accept
之前国会不是已经接受
Cai Yuanpei's proposal before?
罢兔蔡元培的提案了吗
Why did you retract it?
怎么又给打回来了
It wasn't the petition group that caused it.
还不是这请愿团闹的
Because the war in Europe was won,
因为欧战胜利了
the patriotic enthusiasm of Chinese people is unprecedentedly high.
国人的爱国热情空前地高涨
Now there's another Qingdao petition group
这会儿又闹出个青岛请愿团
that immediately won the support of the people.
立马就博得民众的支持
And the Northern and Southern governments being at odds
而南北政府不和
has always been complained of by the people.
素来就被民众所诉病
It's very difficult to get a Paris Peace Conference,
好不容易逮看个巴黎和会
which can divert your attention.
能转移一下视线
At this juncture,
在这个节骨眼上
naturally, there will be no more trouble.
自然就不会多生事
This is not a retraction.
这不就给打回来了
These people are really cunning.
这几个老东西还真是老好巨猾
Uncle, what should we do next?
二叔 那我们接下来该怎么办
You're at Peking University every day,
你天天在北大
and you didn't notice
你就没有发现
what their new trends are?
他们有什么新的动向
There's one thing.
倒还真有件事
Jinwan,
金弯
go to that house.
去那个屋吧
Uncle, Cai Yuanpei and Chen Duxiu have taken the lead recently
二叔 最近蔡元培和陈独秀挑头
to set up a Work-Study Mutual Aid Society
搞了一个工读互助社
that's said to experiment with anarchism
说是要实验无政府主义
and communism,
和共产主义
and also open to the community
还面向社会招募
to enlist many people
竟然真有不少人
who come from afar.
从外地赶过来报名
Mutual aid society...
互助社
Communism...
共产主义
Go back to school.
回学校去
Keep an eye on this mutual aid society.
给我盯紧了这个互助社
Do you think there are articles to write here?
您觉得 这里边有文章可做
This kind of corrupt and filthy society
这种伤风败俗 龌龊的社团
has the responsibility and obligation
有责任 有义务
to expose its true face to the public.
向民众揭露他们的真面目
Yes, I understand.
好 我知道了
Come and sit, one and all!
来一来 坐一坐
I'm in a really good mood today.
今天的心情是真不错
You say one thing and I say another, helping each other is the truth.
你一言我一语 互相帮助是真理
Come on, come on, sit down
来来来 快入座
Come and listen to Yannian
来听延年把话说
speak.
来把话说
Students, take some stools.
同学们 把凳子搬好了
Let's sit down.
咱们就入座啊
Let's have a formal meeting today.
今天咱们正式开会
[Chen Yannian, eldest son of Chen Duxiu]
[陈延年 陈独秀长子]
Students,
同学们
today is a memorable day.
今天是一个值得纪念的日子
The first experimental group
我们北京工读互助社
of the Beijing Work-Study Mutual Aid Society is born.
第一实验小组诞生了
Students, from now on,
同学们 从现在开始
the thirteen of us
我们十三个人
are all members of a big family.
就是一个大家庭的成员了
Everyone in the society calls each other comrades.
社内大家互称同志
Do you have any objection?
诸位没有什么异议吧
Agreed.
同意
Agreed, agreed, agreed.
同意同意同意
Starting from today,
从今天开始
we are
我们就是有着
comrades with common ideals and beliefs.
共同理想和信念的同志了
All right, comrades.
那好 诸位同志们
Let's introduce ourselves to each other first.
我们就先来互相自我介绍一下
Who comes first?
谁先来
I'll go first.
我先来吧
Go ahead.
来
Hello, comrades. My name is Shi Cuntong.
同志们好 我叫施存统
[Shi Cuntong, Student at Zhejiang First Provincial Normal School]
[施存统 浙江省立第一师范学生]
I'm from Jinhua County in Zhejiang.
浙江金华人
Born in 1899.
一八九九年生
I'm a student at Zhejiang First Provincial Normal School.
是浙江第一师范学校的学生
The reason why I came to Beijing
我之所以来北京
to join our Work-Study Mutual Aid Society
参加咱们工读互助社
is because I yearn for,
是因为我向往
I yearn for a kind of anarchy
我向往一种无政府
with no power, no law,
无强权 无法律
no religion, no marriage,
无宗教 无婚姻
an ideal life without family.
无家庭的理想生活
And I think our Work-Study Mutual Aid Society
而我认为咱们工读互助社
is this kind of life.
就是这样的生活
I understand the so-called work-study mutual aid
我理解的所谓工读互助
is labor
工是劳动
and hard work,
读是劳心
and mutual aid is evolution.
而互助是进化
Our members work hard,
我们社员们一边劳动 一边劳心
work all their lives, and study all their lives.
终生工作 终生学习
What a joy!
其乐无穷啊
I hereby swear to all comrades,
这里 我向各位同志宣誓
that from this day onwards
从今天起
I am the society and the society is me.
我即是社 社即是我
The interests of the society
社的利害
is thus my personal interest.
就是我施存统个人的利害
Hurrah!
好 好
Hello, comrades. My name is Yu Xiusong.
同志们好 我叫俞秀松
[Yu Xiusong, Student at Zhejiang First Provincial Normal School]
[俞秀松 浙江省立第一师范学生]
I'm from Zhuji County in Zhejiang.
浙江诸暨人
Born in 1899.
一八九九年生
Like Shi Cuntong,
我跟施存统一样
I am a student at Zhejiang First Provincial Normal School.
都是浙江第一师范学校的学生
Yesterday I wrote
昨天我给我的父母
a long letter to my parents
写了一封长信
in which I explained in detail
信里边详细地解释了
why I came to Beijing
我为什么要来北京
and the reasons for joining the Work-Study Mutual Aid Society,
参加工读互助社的原因
which mentions
其中提到
that my purpose
我的目的
is to experiment with my ideal life
是想实验我的理想生活
and spread it to all mankind
想传播到全人类
so that they can enjoy this new life
使他们共同享受这份甘美
of happiness, love, mutual aid, and freedom
快乐 博爱 互助 自由的新生活
together!
才算完事
Hurrah!
好
Hello, everybody!
大家好
My name is He Mengxiong. I'm from Lingxian County in Hunan.
我叫何孟雄 湖南酃县人
[He Mengxiong, Visiting student at Peking University]
[何孟雄 北京大学旁听生]
Born in 1898.
一八九八年生
Now I'm studying in at the French Language Institute
现在法文专修馆学习
and attending Peking University at the same time.
同时 在北大旁听
I want to join a mutual aid society
我参加互助社
because I want to try a new life.
就是想尝试一种新的生活
I have no other desires.
别无他求
Exactly! Me too!
没错 我也一样
Sorry for being too rash.
冒昧 冒昧
Hello, comrades. My name is Yi Qunxian.
同志们好 我叫易群先
[Yi Qunxian]
[易群先]
I ran out because I opposed my parents' forced marriage.
是因为反对父母逼婚跑出来的
I'm here for the same reason as Comrade He,
我来这儿的目的呢跟何同志一样
that is to want to live a free and open life.
就是想过上自由 开放的生活
Nothing?
没了
Okay, this is the notebook of our mutual aid society.
好 这是咱们互助社的记事本
Let's pass it on and talk about it.
咱们边传边说
How many are there?
那边是几个
Six people.
六个人
Here.
来
Comrades,
同志们
the first experimental group of our Work-Study Mutual Aid Society
咱们工读互助社第一实验小组
will officially open tomorrow.
从明天开始就要正式地开张了
The small courtyard on the west side of the entrance of the French study hall
法文进修馆大门西边那个小院
has already been rented by us.
我们已经租下来了
A few houses in the back
后面几间房子
will be a dormitory for non-local members.
给外地来的社员当宿舍
The front rooms facing the street
前面几间临街的
will be used as a canteen.
咱们用来当食堂
Work-study and public ownership of property.
半工半读 财产公有
Bai Lan,
白兰
announce our financial status
你跟大家公布一下
to everyone.
咱们的财产状况
Ok.
好
The initial funds are all here now.
启动资金现在全都在这儿了
Let me show you.
我给大家看一下
It's 523 yuan in total.
一共呢 是五百二十三块大洋
Of this amount,
这其中
350 yuan is donated by the community.
社会各界捐赠三百五十块大洋
Membership fees and donations by members
社员的入社费和社员捐赠
totals 173 yuan.
一共一百七十三块大洋
Regarding working, let me explain it first.
关于打工呢我先说明一下
I, Qiaonian, and Guo
我和乔年还有老郭
will be doing distribution for "New Youth".
我们三个人在《新青年》搞发行
Bai Lan will work as a tutor in the embassy district.
白兰在使馆区当家教
Keep doing all this.
这些都继续做
It's just that revenue must be collectively owned.
只是工钱必须要交公
Now, we will implement three businesses.
我们现在落实到三样业务
First, a work-study canteen that needs six people.
一是工读食堂 需要六个人
Second, four people to wash clothes.
二是洗衣服 需要四个人
Third, three people to show movies.
三是放电影 需要三个人
Let's discuss
这三项业务
these three businesses.
咱们大家商量一下
No need to discuss.
不用商量
I'll run the canteen.
我来搞食堂
Xingang. Yannian.
心刚 延年
Bai Lan. Liu Mei.
白兰柳眉
If you guys have nothing to do at times,
你们几个平时要没事的话呀
just come and assist me.
过来给我打打下手就行
OK. No problem.
行 没问题
No problem. I'll tell you what,
没问题 我跟你说
Qingdao will be back soon.
青岛马上就要回来了
I'm in a good mood these past two days.
我老郭这两天心情大好
Don't say that I'll "assist" you,
别说给你打下手了
it sounds like I'd be a servant.
就是当仆人都行
Then I'll do the laundry.
那我负责洗衣服吧
Count me in!
算我一个
Count me in too.
也算我一个
Good!
好
I'm good for nothing.
我什么都不会
I'll play the movies.
我 我放电影
What do you mean you're good for nothing? That's easy.
什么都不会 那好办呀
You're a good-for-nothing.
你什么都不会
Joined the mutual aid society.
来到了互助会
Showing movies is too hard for you.
放电影可是高难度
You really are a good-for-nothing.
你不会也得会
Great!
好
Well said!
说得好
Ok, everyone is sleeping well.
行啊 一个个睡得挺香啊
Stop sleeping!
让你们睡
Who is it?
谁呀
Who are you?
你谁呀
Yu Xiusong!
俞秀松
Everyone, get up! You know what time it is?
都起床了 几点了
I said what are you yelling about in the middle of the night?
我说你这大半夜喊什么
Are you sleepwalking?
你梦游啊
Middle of the night?
大半夜
Still asleep, still asleep!
还睡 还睡
What are you doing?
干吗呀
Get up! Stop sleeping!
起床 别睡了
What are you calling for in the middle of the night?
大半夜的喊什么你
Middle of the night? Do you know what time it is?
大半夜 你知道现在几点吗
Do you know what day it is today?
知道今天什么日子吗
What day?
什么日子
Qiaonian, don't drag my blanket.
乔年 别拽我被子
Today is the first day of the work-study canteen.
今天工读食堂开业第一天
We buy rice at 6:30.
六点半买饭
It's 6:00 now!
现在都六点了
I almost missed something big.
差点误大事了
Qiaonian! Wake up, wake up!
乔年 快起快起
What's up? The chicken hasn't crowed yet.
起什么起啊 鸡还没打鸣呢
What noise when it's dawn?
天都亮了 打什么鸣啊
Wash yourself!
收拾你
Get up quickly!
快起来
Where are you going?
你干吗去
I waited all night for their crowing.
等它们打鸣等了一晚上
I'll deal with them.
我收拾它们去
Guo, go and call the girls.
老郭 你快去喊女同志啊
The girls?
还女同志
The girls got up early to help.
女同志早起来帮忙了
You boys are worse than the girls.
你们这帮男同志连女同志都不如
Fools!
丢人
Come, come! Time to eat!
来来来 吃饭了啊 吃饭
Come here.
过来
Eat!
吃饭了
I almost got up late
该叫你不叫
because of you not crowing!
害得我差点起晚了
You didn't crow when you should've crowed!
该打鸣你不打鸣
Don't you know what your job is?
知道你是干什么工作的吗
Comrades who got up late.
晚起的男同志们
You guys can go back to sleep again.
你们再回去接茬睡吧
I'll tell the sun
我跟太阳说一声
to come back out later.
让它等会儿再出来
We comrades who got up late
那我们晚起的男同志
bow to the women who got up early.
向早起的女同志先鞠一躬
No, don't, you don't have to.
别别别 受不起
Late risers,
晚起的男同志们
why don't you go back to sleep?
你们还是回去接着睡吧
We don't need you here.
这儿不需要你们
Come on!
来来来
I feel ashamed.
惭愧 惭愧
Late risers,
那个那个 晚起的男同志
look at how beautifully the yard
你看看人家早起的女同志
and stove are cleaned
和一未没睡的海威同志
by the women who got up early
把这个院子
and Comrade Hai Wei who didn't sleep.
还有灶台打扫得多漂亮
All thanks to our Shandong chef.
这多亏了我们的山东大厨
Late risers, go back to sleep.
晚起的男同志你接着回去睡
Women who get up early don't feel tired when they work.
早起的女同志她干活不觉得累
Comrade Yannian, listen carefully.
延年同志你仔细听
The frugal canteen opens today.
俭洁食堂今日开张
What was it again?
什么来着
The best in China!
全中国之最
Yes, yes, yes!
对对对
Hurry up!
快快快
Come on!
来来来
Open for business!
挂牌 开张
Open up! Let's go!
开张 走 走
Yes, yes, yes!
对对对
Good!
好
Is that OK?
可以吗
Looks good!
好 好
Comrades,
同志们
the frugal canteen is our home.
俭洁食堂就是我们的家了
Let's go, comrades!
同志们 加油
Let's go!
加油
Open up!
开张
Let's work!
干活
Let's go to work!
走 干活
"Time flows like water,"
光阴似流水
"Soon we shall depart from school,"
不一会课毕放学归
"We will ponder for a while"
我们仔细想一会
"to understand today's homework,"
今天功课明白未
"Have we ever gone against our teacher?"
老师讲的话可曾有违背
"Parents want children to come home,"
父母望儿归
"We should not wander on the road"
我们一路莫徘徊
"of leading the country's future and the world"
将来治国平天下
"which depends on our generation,"
全靠吾辈
"Everybody, let's work hard!"
大家努力呀
"See you again tomorrow, classmates."
同学们 明天再会
Let's go, everyone!
大家加油
Let's go!
加油
Oil cakes! Steamed buns!
油饼 包子
Freshly baked oil cakes!
刚出锅的油饼
Come and try it!
您来尝尝吧
Yes, please try the oil cakes
对 您来尝尝油饼
and steamed buns!
还有刚蒸的包子
Cheap and good quality.
干净 物美价廉
Keep yelling, keep yelling.
接着吆喝 接着吆喝
We're selling breakfast here.
在这儿卖早餐啊
Morning, sir.
先生早
Come on, come on, students!
来来来 同学们
Our first order for today!
我们今天第一单的客人
Welcome.
欢迎
Hello, sir.
先生好
Hello, Mr. Shizhi.
适之先生好
Good morning, everyone.
大家早上好
Sir,
先生
it's still hot just after coming out of the pot.
刚出锅 还热乎呢
Please have one.
您来一份吧
Mr. Shizhi, have some oil cakes and steamed buns.
适之先生 来点油饼和包子吧
It's cheap here.
我们这儿便宜
Yes, try it.
对您尝尝
Try it.
您尝尝
[Hu Shi, styled Shizhi, Professor at Peking University]
[胡适 字 适之 北京大学教授]
Okay, I'll have a taste.
好 我尝一尝
Delicious!
香
Isn't it?
是不是
How is it?
怎么样
Tastes good!
真香啊
Isn't it?
是不是
Try some more.
多吃点 都尝尝
Try them all. Try them all.
都尝尝 都尝尝
I think we need to promote
我觉得咱们俭洁食堂啊
our frugal canteen.
得好好宣传宣传
Find a newspaper to sponsor advertising.
找一个报纸赞助 登广告
Take a picture of the four words
把门口那四个字还有那副对联
and the couplet at the entrance and put it up.
给它拍下来 登上去
That's your signature!
那可是你们招牌啊
Right.
对哈
The four words on our plaque were written by Mr. Cai.
咱们牌匾上四个字是蔡先生写的
This couplet on both sides
两旁的这个对联
was written by Mr. Lu Xun.
是鲁迅先生题的
You see?
看看啊
You didn't make good use
这么好的资源
of such a good resource.
你们没有好好利用起来
Isn't it a pity?
是不是可惜了
Good idea, sir.
先生说的好主意
Our student union can also help.
我们学生会也可以帮忙啊
I'll have to trouble you then.
到时候可得麻烦你们了
Everybody make good use of this resource.
大家把这个资源利用好
Do you have steamed buns and oil cakes?
有包子和油饼没有
We do!
有有有
Mr. Shouchang!
守常先生好
Students,
同学们
[Li Dazhao, styled Shouchang, Director of Peking University Library]
[李大钊 字 守常 北京大学图书馆主任]
your second order is here!
你们第二单生意来了啊
Shizhi, you also come to buy breakfast.
适之 你也来买早点
I'm not here to buy breakfast.
我不是来买早点的
I am their volunteer publicist.
我是他们的义务宣传员
Mr. Shouchang,
守常先生
today is the first day of opening
今天是我们俭洁食堂
of our frugal canteen.
第一天开张
How can you support us?
怎么给我们捧捧场呢
I'm here to pay tribute.
我来这儿就是捧场来的
This place is really nice.
这个地儿弄得真不错
Good, good.
好好好
Yannian,
延年
an oil cake and a bowl of porridge.
一个油饼 一碗粥
Yes, sir, please sit down.
好勒 先生请坐
Okay.
好
An oil cake and a bowl of porridge!
一个油饼 一碗粥
Okay!
好勒
An oil cake and a bowl of porridge are not enough.
一个油饼一碗粥不够啊
Mr. Shouchang is so big,
守常先生那么大的个
he needs to have three oil cakes and three bowls of porridge.
必须 三个油饼三碗粥
I can't eat so much.
我吃不了这么多
How many oil cakes did you eat?
你吃了几个油饼啊
I have family rules.
我有家规
I can't eat breakfast outside.
我不能在外边吃早点
Do you have any money?
没带钱吧
Yannian,
延年
three oil cakes and three bowls of porridge.
三个油饼三碗粥
I and Mr. Shizhi will eat here.
我和适之先生在这儿吃了
Mr. Shouchang.
守常兄
Yannian!
延年
No, family rules are family rules.
不行 家规就是家规
I can't break them.
我不能破啊
You know what?
这样吧
I'll tell your aunt Dongxiu tomorrow morning
我明天早上给你冬秀婶子说
to stop making breakfast.
别做早餐了
Let's have breakfast together at the frugal canteen.
我们俩一块来俭洁食堂吃早点
How about that?
怎么样
Alright!
好啊
Okay!
好
I'm leaving, brother Shouchang.
我走了 守常兄
Students, work hard!
同学们 辛苦啊
See you later.
一会儿见
Goodbye, sir.
先生再见
Sir, walk slowly.
先生慢走
Guo,
老郭
I'm leaving, too.
我也走了啊
I will come again tomorrow.
明天我还来啊
I can give you the bill.
我可给你记账了啊
I'll pay later!
挂账 挂账
Come tomorrow.
明天来啊
See you tomorrow!
明天见
The little fatty can eat quite well,
小胖子还挺能吃
that fatty.
这胖子
Yannian,
延年
come here.
来
Here is ten yuan for you.
这儿有十个大洋 押你们这儿
I will come here for breakfast every day in the future.
以后我天天来这儿吃早点
This is inappropriate, sir.
这不合适 先生
All your money goes to the poor.
您的钱都接济穷人了
Don't listen to them.
别听他们害说
Mr. Cai actually deducts thirty dollars a month
蔡先生其实每个月扣下三十大洋
and sends it directly to my wife.
直接给我夫人送过去
So I have no worries here.
所以我这儿呢也没有什么顾虑
You also don't have any ideas.
你们也别有什么想法
Thank you, sir.
谢谢先生
It's really good.
真香
Comrades!
同志们
The first official order,
第一单正式的生意
ten yuan!
十个大洋
Business is booming!
生意兴隆啊
Thank you, sir.
谢谢先生
You say you're such a big man.
你说你这么大的人了
What are you angry with the children about?
跟孩子们置什么气
I'm ashamed of you.
我都替你害臊
You can't talk nonsense.
话不能乱讲啊
I'm not angry with him.
我可没跟他置气
You're not angry with them.
你没跟他们置气
Why don't you let me go to the frugal canteen to buy breakfast?
干吗不让我去俭洁食堂买早餐
Dad,
爸爸
I also want to eat breakfast cooked by Yannian.
我也想吃延年哥哥做的早餐
I want to eat, too.
我也想吃
[Chen Duxiu, styled Zhongfu, Dean of Liberal Arts at Peking University]
[陈独秀 字 仲甫 北京大学文科学长]
Isn't there food at home?
那家里有吃的
Why do you want to buy it?
干吗要去买呀
There is no place to spend money.
有钱没地方花呀
You said,
你说你
the frugal canteen opened on the first day today,
那俭洁食堂今天第一天开张
and I shouldn't have given them a boost.
我不该给他们加加势啊
You went today, will you go tomorrow?
你今天去了 你明天去不去
Since it is an experiment, it needs objective facts.
既然是实验 那就要客观事实
The results are valuable.
得出的结果才有价值
Let them rely on themselves.
让他们靠自己吧
All right, let's eat.
行了 你们踏实吃吧
Why are you going?
你干吗去
I filled all the porridge for you.
我把粥都给你盛好了
I'm full.
我吃饱了
I'm going to have a look around
我 我去转转
and digest the food.
消化消化食
Stop wiping.
别擦了
This table is polished like a mirror.
这桌子擦得跟镜子一样
There's not one guest here. Why are you cleaning it?
这一个客人也没有 你擦它干吗
What's going on?
怎么回事啊
You can't sell a single oil cake.
一个油饼都卖不出去
Stop frying.
别炸了
What's the use of frying so much?
炸那么多有什么用啊
There aren't any guests, it's a waste to fry.
一个客人都没有 炸了也是浪费
Not how your words sound to my ears.
不是你这话我听着怎么扎耳朵呢
What is waste?
什么叫浪费呀
This cake won't sell.
这饼卖不出去
There is something wrong with your publicity.
就是你们招揽有问题
We've been dragging
我们拉了呀
people here all morning.
一上午都在拉人
What are you talking about?
说什么呢
You made the oil cake. There is something wrong with it.
是你做的油饼有问题
I'm telling you, you have a skills problem.
那我还说呢 你技术有问题
I have a skills problem?
我技术有问题
Yeah!
对
Mr. Hu Shi said my cake was delicious.
胡适先生都说我的饼好吃
Then I don't think your cake is delicious.
那我认为你那饼不好吃
Why don't you go out and get people?
你们怎么不出去揽人去
A group of people have been sitting there all morning.
一帮人坐那儿坐了一上午
Guo was sleeping.
老郭都睡着了
Why don't you go?
你怎么不去呀
Okay, okay!
行行行
This is our first day of opening,
咱们今天第一天开张
it's normal to have concerns.
人家心有顾虑是正常
Take your time, this thing can not be rushed.
慢慢来 这事急不得
Why do you have concerns?
为什么会有顾虑呀
Why don't you go?
你怎么不去啊
Okay, okay, I won't argue with you all.
行了行了 我不跟你们说
Do what you want.
爱怎么着怎么着
What kind of attitude is that?
什么态度 你
It's urgent.
这事急不得
Everyone.
各位
Business is booming?
生意兴隆啊
Hello, Mr. Zhongfu.
仲甫先生好
Please sit down, sir.
先生 您快请坐
Please, please.
请请请
Make room for sir. Go, go, go.
给先生腾地儿 快快快
Come here.
来来来
Sit down, sir.
先生 您坐
Mr. Zhongfu,
仲甫先生
you haven't had breakfast yet, have you?
您还没吃早饭吧
No, no, no.
没吃 没吃
What can I get here?
来点什么
What do you have here?
你们这儿有什么呀
How many do we have here?
我们这几有
Don't serve him.
不卖
Why don't you serve him?
怎么就不卖了呢
Yannian!
延年
We don't need his sympathy.
不需要同情
Chen Yannian.
陈延年
This is our business.
这是我们大伙的生意
It's not up to you alone.
你一个人说了 不算
Sir, you're kidding.
先生 您见笑啊
Let me introduce to you what we have.
我给您介绍一下吧
We have porridge, steamed buns, oil cakes
我们这儿有粥 包子 油饼
and soy milk.
还有豆浆
And the soy milk
而且豆浆还是
was freshly ground by me this morning.
我早上起来现磨的
Then I'll have a bowl of soy milk
那就来一碗豆浆
and an oil cake.
还有一个油饼
Got it!
好勒
One is not enough.
一个不够啊
Sir, Mr. Dazhao was here this morning.
先生 大钊先生早上来过了
He ordered three oil cakes
他一个人就点了三张油饼
and three bowls of soy milk.
三碗豆浆
He eats so much!
他吃那么多呀
Right.
对
Then give me two oil cakes
那给我来两张油饼
and one bowl of soy milk.
一 一碗豆浆
Got it!
好勒
Go, go!
得勒 得勒
Okay, okay, I'll go. I'll go
好好 我去 我去
Please wait a moment, sir.
先生您稍等啊
This is a fresh cake
这是 新鲜饼
Here is one cake, fresh out of the pan.
先给您来一张 刚出锅的
Not bad.
还不错
Try the freshly ground soy milk.
现磨的豆浆 您尝尝
Nice.
好 好
Good.
好
You guys get busy.
你们去忙吧
Okay.
好的
Enjoy your meal, sir.
先生您慢用
Please enjoy your meal, sir.
先生 您慢吃
You guys are looking at me eating.
你看我这生意做的
Comrades,
同志们
although it is a small business,
我们俭洁食堂今天第一天开业
our frugal canteen has just opened its first day today.
虽然是小本买卖
But,
但是
first, we don't accept sympathy from others.
第一 我们不接受别人的同情
second, we do not forgive bills.
第二 不允许除账
That Fu Sinian got up in the morning
那傅斯年早上起来
and I just cancelled his bill.
可是刚挂了账啊
Fu Sinian is a student.
傅斯年是学生
From now on, everyone except students
从今往后 除了学生
cannot cancel the bill.
谁都不能赠账
Guo.
老郭
You keep an eye on it.
你给盯紧了啊
If someone doesn't pay for the meal today,
今天要是吃饭不给钱
don't let them out of this door.
千万别让他出这个门
We must resolutely resist freeloading.
要坚决抵制吃白食
Who are you talking about?
说谁呢
What freeloading?
什么吃自食的
What insinuating remarks.
含沙射影的
Why do you eat and eat, and yet are anxious?
您怎么吃着吃着还吃急眼了呀
You don't have any money, do you?
您没带钱啊
I- I- I-
我我我
I left in a hurry. I forgot.
我走得急我忘了
That won't do.
那这可不行
What should I do if you don't have any money?
您没带钱这怎么办
What can I do?
有什么怎么办的
I- I- I- I'll go back.
我我我 我回
I'm sure I'll give you the money then.
到时候我肯定饭钱会给你的
How can I trust you?
我怎么相信您
If you go out and run away,
您要是出去了跑了
then where can I find you?
那我上哪儿找您去
I- I- I- Where would I go?
我我我 我往哪儿跑啊
I don't know.
那我不知道啊
Look, have you eaten the oil cake?
您看 油饼您吃了吧
Yeah.
吃了
Have you drunk soybean milk?
豆浆您喝了吧
Just a sip.
喝了一口
Then a sip is a drink.
那喝了一口也是喝
Isn't that freeloading?
那不就是吃白食吗
What freeloading?
什么吃吃白食啊
Didn't I tell you?
我不是说了吗
I'll give you the money when I come back.
等我回去取了钱我送过来
We absolutely cannot cancel the bill.
坚决不能除账
I've heard that.
我已经听见了
Didn't Fu Sinian cancel the bill, too?
傅斯年不也则账了吗
There's a difference between you and Fu Sinian.
那傅斯年跟您不一样啊
How about you?
您是谁呀
How much do you earn a month?
您一个月挣多少钱啊
What should I do then?
那怎么办嘛
I just forgot my money.
我就是忘带钱了
I forgot my money. Why?
我忘带钱了 怎么着
Should I give you all my clothes?
我把衣服脱给你
No, no, no.
不不不
We can't take your clothes.
我们不能要您那衣服
How about this?
那这样
We are an anarchist
我们是无政府主义的
communist mutual aid society
共产主义互助社
that follows the principle of mutual assistance.
遵循的就是互助原则
Those who do not work, do not eat.
不劳动者不得食
Go wash the dishes to settle the bill.
洗碗抵账吧
Wash the dishes?
洗碗
That doesn't suit you?
那不行
Chopping firewood, washing clothes, feeding chickens,
劈柴火 洗衣服 喂鸡
milking goats, grinding soybeans,
挤羊奶 磨豆浆
and gluing envelopes.
还有那个糊信封
Anything. You choose.
都都行 您选
Okay, I'll wash the dishes.
行 那我洗碗
Mr. Zhongfu, how can you wash the dishes?
仲甫先生 您怎么能洗碗呢
No, no, no.
别别别
I will follow your rules.
按照你们规矩来
A man without money is no man at all.
一分钱难倒英雄汉
I'll wash the dishes.
我洗碗
Please eat first, then wash after eating.
您先吃吧 吃完再洗
I'll wash it before eating it.
我先洗 再吃吧
Otherwise, I can't eat steadily.
要不然我吃不踏实
Can you beat me? This
能难住我吗这个
Where are your bowls?
碗呢 你们碗在哪儿呢
I'm really sorry.
实在是不好意思啊
You haven't finished your meal yet.
您这饭没吃完呢
You have to wash your own dishes after eating.
您得吃完了饭洗自己的碗
No, Yannian.
不 延年
Chen Yannian
陈延年
You're trying to squeeze your old man, aren't you?
你这是成心挤对你老子是不是
Who pushed you?
谁挤对你了
Hello, madame.
师母好
You also
你们也是
asked your dad to wash your dishes.
让你爸给你们洗碗
He hasn't smashed all your bowls yet.
他还不把你们的碗都给砸了
I knew you didn't have any money.
就知道你没带钱
Yannian, here.
来 延年
This is the money your father gives you.
这是你爸给你的钱
Comrades, the third order!
同志们 第三笔生意啊
Thank you, guests.
谢谢客人
Hold on to this.
入账
Thank you, Mr. Zhongfu.
谢谢仲甫先生
Didn't you have breakfast this morning?
你今儿早上不是吃过早餐了吗
Not full?
没吃饱啊
This morning,
本来今天早上呀
I was the one who wanted to give you a boost first.
是我要先来给你们加加势的
As a result, your father refused
结果你爸不同意
to let me come anyway.
死活不让我来
As a result, I came here first.
结果好 自己倒捷足先登了
The point is, he didn't bring any money.
关键是还没带钱
Liu Mei, Bai Lan.
柳眉 白兰
I'm here for the first time today.
我今天第一次到你们这儿来
Show me around.
带我转转吧
Ok.
好勒 行
This is our chicken and duck.
这是我们养的鸡鸭
This is common property.
这是共有财产
That's the laundry room.
那边是洗衣房
Good, good, good.
真好 真好
You let go!
你放手
I won't let go!
我不放
If you join a mutual aid society,
进了互助社
you must have all communist consciousness.
就要有一切共产的觉悟
This is my personal property. Why should I be communist?
这是我的私人物品凭什么要共产
You let go!
你放手
Will you let go?!
你放不放手
I won't let go!
我不放
Don't you let me shout?
你不放我喊了啊
Shout, then!
你喊
Yu Xiusong.
俞秀松
What are you doing? Let him go.
干吗 松手
Comrade Chen Yannian, you're just in time.
陈延年同志 你来得正好
You reason this out.
你给评评理
I was so excited to join a mutual aid society
参加互助社 实现共产主义
to realize communism that I stayed up all night.
我激动得一宿没睡
Get down.
下来
I put all my clothes away.
我把我的衣服都摆
Now that we're communist,
既然共产了
there can be no more private property.
就不能再有这些私人财产
I laid out all the clothes I brought.
我把我带来的衣服都摆出来了
I think Comrade Yu is a rich boy.
我这一想 俞同志是富家子弟呀
I came to encourage him to put out his clothes.
我就过来动员他把衣服也摆出来
There are three new pants here.
这几有三条新裤子
Guess what?
你猜怎么着
He refused.
他不肯
How unreasonable are you?
你这位女同志好没有道理呀
Everyone, what are your thoughts on this?
大家给我评评理
She came to open my suitcase early in the morning
她一大早跑来开我的箱子
and asked me to hand in my clothes.
让我上交衣裳
This suitcase is full of my personal belongings
这箱子里都是我的私人物品
and school equipment.
和学习用具
Yes, there are pants in it.
是 这里面是有裤子
Those are men's pants. You can't even wear them!
那是男同志裤子你也穿不了啊
You're so unreasonable!
你好不讲道理
Who said I was going to wear your pants?
谁说我要穿你的裤子了
I can't wear your pants.
我穿不了你的裤子
But other comrades can wear it.
可是其他同志能穿呀
What's wrong with you?
你这人怎么这样
You have three new pants here.
你这儿有三条新裤子
Can't you share with those whose pants are worn out?
你就不能分享给裤子已经破了
Or to comrades with only one pair of pants?
或者只有一条裤子的同志们吗
You are still elected by the Social Committee.
亏你还是大家推举的社委呢
Selfish!
自私
I am selfish?
我自私
You're a pants person, aren't you?
你是裤子精吧你
You say "pants" left and "pants" right.
你左一句裤子右一句裤子的
Who says communism must hand in pants?
谁说共产主义一定要上交裤子
Is there such a clause in the constitution of our Work-Study Mutual Aid Society?
咱工读互助社章程里有这一条吗
All right, stop arguing.
行了 别吵了
Do you want to share the members' clothes?
社员的衣服要不要共享
There are no clear rules yet.
还没有明确的规定
You have this idea?
你有这个想法
It can be submitted to the general assembly for voting.
可以提交大会表决一下
Until then, keep it as it is.
在此之前 维持原状
Time to eat.
开饭
Chairman.
委员长
Minister Chen has arrived.
陈总长到了
Master Bo.
伯公
What important documents?
什么重要文件
Minister Chen has to deliver it himself.
要陈总长亲自送来呀
[Chen Lu, styled Renxian, Acting Foreign Minister]
[陈箓 字 任先 代理外交总长]
See for yourself.
您自己看吧
What's going on here?
这是怎么回事
It's been rejected, and returned unchanged.
拒不接受 原样退回
What's the matter?
出了什么事了
Last night, Japan's envoy to China, Xiao Yun, met with me
昨晚 日本驻华公使小幡约见我
and the envoys of the United States, Britain, Italy and France
和美英意法四国公使
and claimed that the core of the Shandong Peninsula issue
声称 山东半岛问题的核心
was not the interests of China and Germany,
不是中国和德国的利益
but the interests of Japan and Germany.
而是日本和德国的利益
We asked that at the Paris Peace Conference...
要求我们在巴黎和会上
Don't make a big deal out of it.
不要节外生枝
Early this morning,
今天一早
President Xu brought Wu Bingxiang and me together
徐大总统就把我和吴炳湘
and asked me
找在一起
to return this petition
要求我把这请愿书和万民折
and the people's statement to you
退还给您
He asked Wu Bingxiang to take measures.
要求吴炳湘采取措施
No more slogans and leaflets appeared on the streets of Beijing.
北京街头再不能出现标语和传单
Then the embassies of the United States, Britain, France and Italy
紧接着 美英法意四国使馆
also returned all the invitation letters from Qingdao.
也将青岛的呼请信悉数退回
Outrageous.
岂有此理
Can spilled water be recovered?
泼出去的水还能收回来吗
What does Xu Shichang want?
徐世昌他要干什么
He's playing with me like a monkey.
拿我当猴耍
Don't you want Qingdao?
青岛不要了吗
President Xu also asked me to tell you
徐总统还让我转告您
that he still wants Qingdao,
青岛还是要要的
we should pay attention to strategy.
但是 要讲究策略
Don't boil the Japanese.
别把日本人煮毛了
If you can't bear it, you will make great plans.
小不忍则乱大谋
He knows how to endure.
忍 他就知道忍
Be patient when you are defeated.
打败了要忍
If you win, you have to endure it.
打胜了还要忍
I think this country is possessed.
我看这个国家是中了邪了
Weak countries have no diplomacy. This is an iron law.
弱国无外交 这是铁律
Then what is justice?
那还讲什么公理呀
What about the embassies of the four countries?
那四国使馆是怎么回事
Wilson's words don't count either?
威尔逊的话也不算数了吗
When the U.S. Embassy returned the letter,
美国使馆在退回信的时候
it emphasized
特别强调
that the U.S. attitude towards China
美国对中国的态度
has always been consistent.
一直是保持一致的
I don't think so.
我看未必啊
This is a signal
这就是信号
that the Paris Peace Conference is in trouble.
巴黎和会要惹麻烦
Master Bo, it already is.
伯公 已经有麻烦了
What happened?
怎么了
When the delegation received
代表团在接到
the ranking of domestic personnel,
国内人员排名的时候
it was already in an uproar.
已经闹炸了天
Wang Zhengting cursed President Xu.
王正廷大骂徐大总统
for discriminating against the Southern government.
歧视南方政府
Shi Zhaoji took the load off his shoulders.
施肇基撂了挑子
Lu Zhengxiang simply went to Switzerland.
陆征祥干脆跑瑞士去了
Now it's all up to Gu Weijun.
现在全靠顾维钧在做周旋
This is to be expected.
这是意料之中的
I have sent telegrams to Lu Zhengxiang
我已分别给陆征祥
and Gu Weijun respectively,
和顾维钧发了电报
and Gu Weijun sends back replies daily.
日常由顾维钧出面
When it's critical, Lu Zhengxiang must come out.
关键时候陆征祥必须出马
It's admirable that the chairman
委员长运筹雌幅 决胜千里
has won a great victory.
令人佩服
There is still trouble at home.
麻烦还是在国内
Cao Rulin, Zhang Zongxiang, Lu Zongxing.
曹汝霖 章宗祥 陆宗興
These people are despicable.
这些人太可恶
The pro-Japanese faction can't be underestimated.
亲日派嘛 势力不容小處
After all is said,
说来说去
all still depend on the foreigners.
还是要看外国人的脸色
Truly a shame!
真是太窝囊了
Please.
请
This is recommended by Mr. Dazhao.
是大钊先生推荐的呀
That's right.
对
Okay, sit down.
好 来 坐
Thank you.
谢谢
The Work-Study Mutual Aid Society
工读互助社呢
is a new thing that everyone is very concerned about.
是大家非常关注的新事物
Of course, it's what our newspaper is interested in
当然也是我们报社所感兴趣
and reported before.
之前予以报道过的
Miss Liu, what about the list
柳小姐您这次来呀
you provided this time?
提供的这份名录呢
In principle?
原则上呢
It can be classified as social news.
它可以被归属为社会类新闻
We have no problem publishing it.
我们刊登没有问题
However, the introduction of the canteen,
但是 您讲到的这个食堂啊
laundry
洗衣社
and film screening group you mentioned
包括电影放映组的介绍
is actually in the advertising category.
其实是属于广告类
There is a fee.
是要收费的
Miss Liu, did you know that?
不知柳小姐您这边是否知晓呢
The Work-Study Mutual Aid Society is full of students.
工读互助社里都是学生
Work-study is a part-work and part-study programme.
工读就是勤工俭学
We have no money to advertise.
我们肯定是没有钱做什么广告了
I'm here to apply
我这次来就是想申请一下
and see if your newspaper can sponsor us.
看看贵报能不能赞助我们一下
Miss Liu,
柳小姐 您这样呢
it's actually embarrassing for us,
其实让我们很为难
because your sponsorship
因为您这样的赞助
is difficult to pass at the board meeting.
在董事会上是很难通过的
I can give you an idea.
我呢倒是可以出一个主意
Go on.
您说
Not only do you need to advertise,
不仅不用你们登广告
but you only need to write a press release.
只需要来写一篇新闻稿
You find a reporter
你找一个记者
to unify your canteens,
把你那些食堂呀
including laundry
包括洗衣社呀
and film screening groups,
包括电影放映组
do an interview
统一呢做一个采访
and write a press release.
写成一篇新闻稿
Not only can it be published in newspapers,
不仅可以在报纸上发表
but other media will reprint it.
而且其他媒体也会予以转载
In this case,
这样子的话
not only did it not cost a penny,
不仅没花一分钱
but this kind of influence
而且这种影响
will also produce great results.
也会产生很大的成效啊
That's good.
那这很好啊
Or ask the editor-in-chief
那要不就请主编
to write a report.
帮我们写一篇报道吧
Young lady.
小姑娘
You are still too honest.
你呢还是太实诚
Not only do you have to find this reporter yourself,
这个记者呀不仅得你们自己去找
it's better to be a columnist.
最好还得是专栏型记者
If you're lucky,
运气好的话呀
maybe he will even pay you an interview fee.
说不定他还会付你一笔采访费呢
I don't know your business either.
我也不了解你们这行
I don't know where to start
我不知道该从哪儿
to find a reporter like this.
去找这样的记者
Mr. Xie,
老谢
you are half-hearted during this work.
你这工作期间三心二意的
It's against the social rules.
这可违反社规啊
Zhang, you're here.
老张 你来了
Here, the manuscript has been delivered to you.
来 稿子给你送来了
Good.
好
Here,
这样
Miss Liu, you are so lucky.
柳小姐 你运气可真好
Let me introduce to you
我给你介绍一下
this young man.
这位呢
He's in charge of our column
是我们《学海要闻》专栏的
"Learning from the Sea",
负责人
and he is also the special director
并且他还兼任着北京和上海
of several newspapers in Beijing and Shanghai.
几家报社的特约负责人
Come on, let's get to know each other.
来 你们认识一下
Hello.
你好
Hello, hello.
你好你好
By the way, Zhang
对了老张
Zhang I remember you said before
我记得你之前说
you are not very interested in understanding
你不是很想了解一下
this Work-Study Mutual Aid Society?
这个工读互助社吗
Then help this Miss Liu.
那你就帮帮这个柳小姐吧
Work-Study Mutual Aid Society is a good subject.
工读互助社可是个好题材呀
I'm very interested.
我非常感兴趣
Thank you, Mr Zhang.
谢谢张先生
Then let's talk somewhere else.
那咱们找个地方谈谈
Isn't it nice here?
这儿不就挺好吗
How can it be here?
这儿哪行啊
The interview is not a matter of three or two sentences.
采访也不是三两句话的事
There is a cafe next to this.
这样 旁边有个咖啡馆
It's my treat.
我请客
Okay.
行
Let's go, then. Please.
走 请
We're going, Mr. Xie.
走了 老谢
Don't bother.
不送
Thank you, editor-in-chief.
谢谢主编
Don't mention it.
不谢
Thank you.
谢谢您
Students,
同学们
the mutual aid frugal canteen has opened.
互助社俭洁食堂开张了
Come next time.
下次来啊
Tired of school meals?
吃腻了学校包饭的
Students, come here.
同学们 到这边来
Yannian!
延年
Come and find out.
过来了解一下呗
Yannian, come!
延年 来
Let me introduce you to some students from the English department.
给你介绍几个英语系的同学啊
They asked if they could pack food and wash clothes.
他们问吃饭和洗衣服能不能打包
and then give them
然后按月结账
a monthly discount.
折扣给点优惠
Okay, no problem.
行行 没问题
Let's come here to discuss.
咱来来来 咱们来这儿商量
Student, who are you looking for to wash clothes?
同学 洗衣服找谁啊
Wash clothes over there!
洗衣服到那边啊
Pack up here.
包伙到这边来
I'll make arrangements for you again.
我再帮你们张罗张罗去啊
Okay, okay.
好的好的
We have someone from Shandong there.
我们那儿有一山东大汉
His cooking is particularly good.
厨艺特别好
There were only two people interested in this movie ticket for half a day.
我这电影票半天只有两个人问津
What should I do?
怎么办呀
You guys are so stubborn.
你们真死心眼
Have you ever seen a group of gentlemen
你哪见过一群大老爷们
go to the movies?
组团看电影的呀
There are no girls in Peking University.
北大没有女生
Who are you selling movie tickets to?
你电影票卖给谁去
So you Peking University students don't watch movies?
那你们北大学生不看电影啊
Let's see.
我们看啊
I went to other schools to accompany my female classmates.
都到别的学校陪女同学看去了
If you really want to sell the tickets,
你们要真想把票卖出去
I'll think of a way for you .
我给你们想个办法啊
Yi Qunxian!
易群先
Coming!
来了
Come here.
来这边
Classmates, come here!
同学们 过来一下
Let me help you solve this problem right away.
马上帮你解决这个问题
I'd like to introduce a female classmate to you today.
我今天给大家介绍一位女同学
Hello all.
你们好
I'm Xie Wanying from Union Women's College Prep.
我是协和女子大学预科的谢婉莹
[Xie Wanying]
[谢婉莹]
Hello.
你好
Hello, hello.
你好你好
Are there many girls in your school?
你们学校女生多吗
We're from a women's university.
我们是女子大学
A women's university.
人家女子大学
Do your school boys watch movies with girls?
你们学校男孩陪女孩看电影吗
Nonsense!
废话
Do you think everyone is like you?
你以为谁都跟你似的呢
It's very cheap for us to package laundry here.
来我们这儿包伙洗衣服 特便宜
We can also have dinner in groups.
我们还可以包伙吃饭
Movie tickets must be popular in your school.
电影票到你们学校肯定受欢迎
People can't hear you clearly.
人家都听不清了
You say it one by one.
你们一个一个说
Sir,
先生
we would like to report to you
我们向您汇报一下
about the establishment
关于成立
of a lecture group on civilian education.
平民教育讲演团的事情
Okay, go on.
好 说说
According to your last suggestion,
根据您上回的建议呢
we discussed it with several societies
我们《国民》 《新潮》
such as "Citizen",
还有马尔克斯研究会
"The Renaissance",
几个社团
and Marxist Research Society.
在一起讨论了一下
We've decided
决定
to set up
先在北大
a school night shift at Peking University first.
成立一个校役夜班
That is, night classes for workers,
也就是工人夜校
three nights a week,
每周呢三个晚上
to popularize culture to workers,
给工友们普及文化
and explain current affairs.
讲解时事
and then we decided
然后我们决定
to formally set up
在这个基础之上
a civilian education lecture group
正式成立
on this basis
平民教育讲演团
to recruit companions
向社会的各界
from all walks of life.
去招募同伴
[Deng Zhongxia, styled Zhongxie, Student at Peking University]
[邓中夏 字 仲澥 北京大学学生]
This is our
这是我们
draft brochure
草拟的简章
and recruitment notice.
还有招募启事
Have a look.
您看一下
Alright.
好
This matter has something to do with Dean Chen.
这件事和陈学长
Have you reported it?
汇报过了吗
We have.
汇报了
Because running a school night shift involves
因为办校役夜班涉及到
the location and funding.
地点和经费的问题嘛
So we
所以我们当时
specifically consulted Dean Chen.
专门请教了陈学长
He was particularly enthusiastic
他特别热心
and asked the superintendent
当时就请度务长
to give us the address
把校役夜班的地址
of the school night shift.
给我们定了下来
Mr. Zhongfu.
仲甫先生
concluded his speech with two sentences
最后还给平民教育讲演团的
about the purpose of the Civilian Education Lecture Group.
宗旨立下了两句话
What two sentences?
哪两句
To enhance civilian knowledge,
增进平民知识
and to arouse the consciousness of common people.
唤起平民自觉心
That brother Zhongfu!
这个仲甫兄啊
Yeah, I haven't forgotten his
是到现在也没忘了他那个
Patriotism and Self-consciousness.
爱国心和自觉心
Good!
好啊
With Mr. Zhongfu's
有了仲甫先生
and Mr. Cai's support,
和蔡先生的支持
this will be easy to handle.
这件事就好办了
I suggest
我建议啊
we find some more people.
我们再多找一些人
to study this
好好地研究一下
this enrollment brochure and articles of association
这个招生简章还有章程
and publish them
然后尽快
in the Peking University journal as soon as possible.
在北京大学的日刊上发表
The main body of the civilian education lecture group
平民教育讲演团的
is students,
主体是学生
but it is not limited
但不仅仅局限于
to the students of Peking University.
北大的学生
It can be used as an organization of the Student Salvation Association.
可以作为学生救国会的 一个组织
This way,
这样
its appeal
它的号召力
will be bigger.
会更大一些
Mr. Shouchang,
守常先生
[Mao Zedong, styled Runzhi, Peking University Library Assistant]
[毛泽东 字 润之 北京大学图书馆助理员]
with that said,
那这样讲的话
I can also sign up.
我也可以报名了
Of course.
当然了
Of course you can sign up.
你当然可以报名了
So then,
那我们现在
let's go and study it.
好好去研究研究
Alright.
好
Let's go.
走
Comrade Liu Mei,
柳眉同志
tell us about the newspaper situation.
说说登报的情况
Okay.
好
The editor-in-chief of the "Morning Post" is a warm-hearted man.
《晨报》的主编 是个热心肠
He introduced me
他给我介绍了
to the reporter of "Learning from the Sea".
《学海要闻》 的记者
The reporter.
那个记者啊
was particularly interested in our Work-Study Mutual Aid Society
对咱们工读互助社特别感兴趣
and said to make for us
说要给咱们做一个
a free series of reports.
免费的系列报道
When I heard it was free,
我一听免费的
I talked to him as hard as I coumd.
我就可劲跟他聊啊
We talked for a long time.
我们俩聊了挺久的
I think it was a good talk.
我觉得谈得还是挺不错的
He said he would come this afternoon
他说今天下午要过来
and give us an interview.
给咱们做个采访
I just want to ask everyone
我就想问问大伙
if they're happy or not.
大伙乐不乐意
If everyone says yes, I'll send him over.
如果大伙说行 我就让他过来
This is a good thing.
这是好事啊
Sure!
可以啊
I think it's negotiable.
我觉得可以商量
Does everyone agree?
大家同意吗
Agree!
同意
He also agrees!
它也同意
Approved!
通过
Hurray! Approved!
好 通过 好
I'm not going. I'm not going.
我可不去 我可不去
How old am I?
我多大年纪了
What kind of night school am I going to? I'm not going!
我还上什么夜校 我不去
Uncle Li!
李大叔
I'm not going. I'm not going.
我可不去 我可不去
I'm not going.
我可不去
Live and learn.
活到老 学到老
I'm not going, I'm not going, I'm not going.
我不去 我不去 不去
Uncle Li!
李大叔
Why are you holding me?
你拉住我干什么
What are you doing?
你干 干啥呢
Let me tell you something.
我跟您说
Uncle Li, I want to say this to you.
李大叔 我为跟您说这一句话
I have already gone to Peking University.
我都跑了一个北大了
I found that your body is better than mine.
我发现了 您这身体比我好
But your health alone doesn't work.
但是您光身体好不管用啊
You say that the words you know now
您说您现在认识的那些字
are not enough for you.
还不够您这一簸算呢
It's embarrassing to say it.
说出去多丢人呀
We open this evening school
我们开这个夜校
to teach reading and writing.
教读书 教认字
It's free.
还是免费的
Many good things.
多好的事
It's free, really?
免费的 真的
It's free.
免费的呀
All the best professors, the best sir.
全是最好的教授 最好的先生
Where else can you find this opportunity?
这您打着灯笼您上哪儿找去呀
Can my son learn?
那我儿子能不能学
Your son?
您儿子
Uncle, it's this:
大叔 是这样
Our night school
我们这夜校
only admits our own workers,
现在只招收咱自己的工友
we don't accept family members.
还不收家属
Then forget it.
那拉倒吧
Then I won't study. I won't study.
那我不学了 不学了
Uncle Li, uncle Li, uncle Li!
李大叔 李大叔 李大叔
He can! He can!
能 能 能
Can he?
能不能
Stop running, stop running.
别跑了 别跑了
He can.
能
I won't run, I won't run.
我不跑不跑
He can. You say:
能 你说
The more people who want to read, the better.
想读书认字的越多越好
I am in charge of this matter.
这事我做主了
The day after tomorrow, you and your son
后天晚上 您和您的儿子
can attend the first class of our evening school.
一起来参加咱们夜校的第一堂课
Is that okay?
您看好不好
Okay, okay, that's what you said.
好好 这可是你说的啊
It's free. It's free.
免费的 不要钱
No money, no money.
不要钱 不要钱
Okay, okay, okay.
那好 那好
Then I'll go home and tell my son
那我回家告诉我儿子去啊
to study the day after tomorrow. Come on!
后天让他来学习来啊
Good.
好
It's a deal, Uncle Li.
咱可说好了 李大叔
Well, I'll go first.
好 那我先走了
Okay, go.
好 您走
Tell my son to go home.
回家告诉我儿子去
I wrote it down for you.
给您记上了啊
good
好
come on
来啊
This child, come again.
这孩子 还来来
See you soon!
不见不散啊
Uncle Wang!
王大爷
Uncle Wang, uncle Wang!
王大爷 王大爷
Our evening classes will start the day after tomorrow.
后天晚上咱们夜校开课了
You must remember to come then.
到时候您一定记得来
Let's settle the matter.
咱们这事就这么定了
Why is that settled?
怎么就这么定了
I don't have the free time.
我可没那闲工夫啊
Uncle Wang!
王大爷
Don't run!
您别跑啊
What's wrong with reading?
读书有什么不好啊
Evening school?
夜校
Yes!
对呀
Do you want to go?
要不要去呀
Don't first ask
你先别问
if we want to go.
要不要去
We want to first ask you:
我们想先问问你
are you kidding us?
是不是跟我们开玩笑的
Not kidding.
没有开玩笑
Our night school
我们这个夜校啊
is specially prepared
就是专门
for our industrial development.
给咱们工发准备的
As long as you want to participate,
只要你们想参加
I'll fill out the form for you.
我给你们填单子
I want to ask you something.
我想问您一下
Can people like me
像我这种人
also go to school?
也能去上学吗
All of us
咱们呀
are the greatest laborers,
是最伟大的劳动者
the most qualified to learn.
是最有资格去学习的
Then I'll go!
那我去
I'll go too!
我也去
Good!
好
I'll register you right away.
我马上给你们登记
Do these masters want to go?
这几位师傅要不要去呀
I'm old.
我年纪大了
I won't go.
就不去啦
Ah, I'm so stupid.
我呀 太笨
I'm so stupid.
我 太笨
I'm scared of not learning.
怕学不会
I don't know a word.
我一个字不认识
It is also a waste of time
去了也是
to go.
自耽误工夫
Paint!
漆
Got it!
好勒
Because we can't read,
就是因为咱们不识字啊
we need to learn more.
才更需要学习
You see,
你们看
for us laborers in Peking University,
我们在北大做役工
what is the most inconvenient thing?
最不方便的是什么呀
A little higher.
高一点
Ah, wait a minute.
稍等啊
Here, master.
来来 小师傅
I'll do it. I'll do it.
我来我来
Here.
我来
Thank you.
谢谢
Here, master.
来师傅
Thank you, thank you.
谢谢 谢谢 谢谢
Thank you.
谢谢
As I said.
我接着说啊
Masters
师傅们
You see,
你们看
for us laborers in Peking University,
我们在北大做役工
the most inconvenient thing
最不方便的
is to speak,
就是会讲
to be able to speak but not write.
会说但不会写
Someone people write.
别人写了呢
We are also not literate.
我们也不识得
Accounts
这个账啊
are sometimes calculated
有的时候会算
but not recorded.
就是记不下来
As you usually say,
就像你们平时说的
it is inconvenient to do anything.
干什么都不方便
You said that
你这话
to my heart.
说到我心坎里了
Look, I'm taking
你看我带着
these collegues to work.
这些工友们做活
Getting materials.
进个料
Dividing the wages.
分个工钱
This,
这个行
I can figure out,
账我能算明白
but I can't write.
可是不会写呀
I'm so worried!
急得我啊
In the house where I live,
我住那个房子里
all the walls are painted with bars.
四面墙上画的全是杠
There are too many bars painted here.
这杠画多了
You don't remember it yourself.
你自己也不记得
I don't remember your salary, and I don't owe you.
我不记得你工钱也没少你的
Not a problem.
没关系
Not anymore.
以后就不会了
Our Peking University
咱们北大呀
has set up a night school
专门为咱们役工啊
for our laborers.
开办了夜校
And
而且呢
all of them are invited by our school's
请的都是咱们学校
most famous teacher
最有名的老师
to teach us to read,
教咱们识字
write letters, and settle accounts.
写信还有算账
Teaching
教的呀
is our most useful knowledge at ordinary times.
都是咱们平时最有用的知识
The key is
关键是
there is no charge for going to school.
上学不收费
Textbooks are also free.
课本呢也是免费的
We are a night school.
我们是夜校
It won't delay our work during the day.
白天呢不耽误我们做工
What a good thing this is!
这是多大的好事呀
What do you mean?
听您这意思
You mean to say
您的意思就是说
that Peking University
就是北大
is giving us poor people
给我们这些穷苦的人
a charity school.
办义学呗
It's not just a charity school,
也不只是义学
it's to respect your
是尊重你们
right to education.
受教育的权利
What is a right?
啥叫权
I'm confused when you say this again.
你说这个我又听糊涂了
That is, Peking University runs an evening school
就是北大办了个夜校
specially for our workers
专门给咱们工人
to gain knowledge.
长知识用的
When we gain knowledge
我们呢 长了知识
and culture,
有了文化
it is convenient for us to do our work.
我们做工作就方便了
You?
您哪
You can also go home and teach your grandchildren.
还可以回家教教您的孙子
For yourself,
对自己
for your families and schools.
对家庭 对学校
Help everyone!
都有帮助
Is it a good thing?
是不是好事呀
Master, don't worry.
几位师傅放心吧
If there is any fee to pay,
如果有任何的费用
you all
你们呀
can come to me:
都可以来找我
Mao Zedong!
毛泽东
Did you hear that?
刚才这番话
Does everyone understand?
听明白没有
We understand!
听明白了
We all
咱们呢
just go to school with peace of mind!
就安心上学
In case someone asks us for money,
万一有人跟咱们要钱
let's find Mao Zedong.
咱们就找毛泽东
Look for me. Look for me.
找我 找我
Good!
好 好
We garden workers
咱们园艺房的人
can now all go to school!
全都去读书